good morning everybody thank you for
tuning in I hope that when you opened
your eyes this morning and you the life
upon which you found yourself having
was one in which you feel you would
deeply went to and that and and that
it's so that you went to it deeply in a
way deserving of you and your attention
in your life and so hopefully this video
and all all the videos that we post here
perhaps make that wedding more available
so I want to set some context really
excited about about this first video but
I want to say some context for the this
first video but also it to be it's gonna
be the first of a series of videos one
in which Chris and I
enact and read through the Platonic
dialogues and we're going to start with
a paper that Chris and John ver Becky
wrote that is precisely about the
restoration and the necessary bringing
forth the Socratic platonic dialogues
and its intelligibility into modernity
into post modernity precisely which I
think will give a very good set a very
good context for how Socratic dialogue
and its mode and its intelligibility is
like perhaps even necessary for our time
first I wanted a little bit of
housekeeping and then we'll all set the
context so
next Friday I start the main thing that
I do professionally which is I teach
circling the practice of circling and we
have our practitioners course which is a
year-long course there are still a few
slots available so if you're interested
in that go down below and click the link
for the art of circling that's the name
of the course so you only have a few
days so if you're if you've been
thinking about it and you haven't done
anything about it now's the time so
definitely check it out also if you are
interested in one-on-one coaching with
me or consulting with me go ahead and
email me and I'll I'll get I'll get in
contact with you and I think that's it
so I'm so excited about this first video
to set context for a series an ongoing
series where Chris and I are going to be
reading the Platonic dialogues and we're
going to be reading the Platonic
dialogues in a particular order and it's
the order that my understanding was the
original way that the Platonic Academy
the first platonic Academy you know way
back and you know ancient Greek you know
before they invented dirt the order in
which you were supposed to read them and
it's interesting because they apparently
the order is that a chronological order
so even in just the order of the
dialogue that we're gonna read it is is
I'm imagining I want to disclose the
intelligence of the order because I'm
imagining that order is the order for a
particular reason okay and you know why
do that why why is why am I excited
about that why bother with that right
what in what do we do it what are we
enacting right when we and I think I'm
gonna call this an act
platonic dialogue OHS so to emphasize as
you've probably heard Jennifer Becky
talked about in his series that you know
not know not philosophy in the in the in
the propositional sense but the
philosophy ax in the whole bodied axis
then like exercising your existential
existential capacity for deep levels of
intelligibility that affect us and
connect us with the various depths
heights and levels of our whole being
and one of the things that I'm really
excited about right in
in this last dialogue I just did with
with Jonathan and and John for Becky it
really it really came together for me
where John had said that that he feels
and all of all of that all of the
investigations he's been doing on ways
in which people are addressing the
meaning crisis's through the various
ecologies of practice you know like
mindfulness meditation circling
authentic relating you know different
forms of embodiment practice all of
these things that are in some way or
dressing what John calls the meeting
crisis and one of the things that one of
the things that John has been saying and
I just really I just really got it was
that that one of the things he finds
missing and I totally agree with him is
is De La Sofia not necessarily
philosophy not the not the academic
propositional kind of philosophy that we
normally associate with philosophy but
but the process of philosophizing right
he's he's what he's saying is it may be
actually perhaps necessary for that
that to also be in with these other
practices of tuning and emotionally of
mindfulness of being in your body of
being embedded in the world
one of them's missing is that sense of
philosophical insight aporia right and
and what he's saying is that like with
without that that it may be necessary to
really address what these practices are
trying to address to be able to have a
connectedness with the you could say the
the ontological level the cognitive
psychological level and the existential
level that without philosophy a--
right that
that's not fully being addressed in a
way that leaves us connected then it may
be necessary and I just I really that
really gathered itself and kind of
showed itself to me when he said it you
know there's been an ongoing process for
me to of learning about it so on one
level the reason why we're doing that is
to explore and to help articulate and
and to begin to show a possible example
of how to do philosophy what that is
what it looks like through doing it
through an abiding everyone else to do
it with us actively or even passively
just watching us so I want this series
to be not not just watching it and and
gaining being informed by something but
actually being formed by it grappling
with it
grappling with what it is to exist what
it is to be human being what is it what
it is to be in a universe in a cosmos
what does any of that stuff even mean
and to dwell in it in such a way that it
can begin to awaken us and then
awakening touch all of the levels of our
existence that on the most abstract
level all the way down to the most
concrete such that we can have a deep
sense of connectedness to the time that
we're in and respond with the deep
intelligence that I believe is what I
believe is indistinguishable from you
being so with
I want to also just read something by
Heidegger that starts to get at that
practice in that space and in
distinguishing it from a different kind
of space that usually involves being
informed of being becoming knowledgeable
all right there's a different there's a
different way of pista episteme a system
ology if you will that there's a way
practicing knowledge right that's
actually an enactment that goes beyond
just being useful right and there's
there's the space of that kind of
knowing that is that is powerful yet not
immediately you you tip like able to be
useful in some kind of technological
optimizing way so Heidegger
this is a lecture I believe it was in
the mid 50's and it was as a lecture
that he I think it's a transcript of a
lecture that he gave for the death of I
think some some big-name kids expect
this physics teacher back then I don't
remember who it is but I'm gonna read
the first three paragraphs and then skip
down to one line because I think it
really highlights and helps that a tone
rings a bell that is that that is the
tone us that that may gather this whole
series going forward because I'm gonna
start the following lecture calls for a
few words of introduction if we were to
be shown right now to pictures by Paul
Klee in the original with
she painted in the year of his death the
watercolor sinks from a window and death
and fire tempera on burlap we should
want to stand before them for a long
while and should abandon any claim that
they'd be immediately intelligible if it
were possible right now to have jord
trials poem serpent of death recited to
us perhaps even by the poet himself we
should want to hear it often and should
abandon any claim that it be immediately
intelligible if Werner Heisenberg right
now were to present some of his thoughts
and theoretical physics moving in the
direction of the cosmic formula for
which he is searching two or three
people in the audience at most would be
able to follow him while the rest of us
would without protest abandon any claim
that he be immediately intelligible not
so with the thinking that is called
philosophy that thinking is supposed to
offer quote worldly wisdom and perhaps
even be a quote way to the blessed life
unquote but it made but it might be
this kind of thinking is today placed in
a position which demands of it
reflection
is far removed from any useful practical
wisdom
it might be that a kind of thinking has
become necessary which you must give
thought to matters from which even the
painting and the poetry which get which
we have mentioned and the theory of
mathematics and physics receive their
determination here too we should then
have to abandon any claim to immediate
intelligibility
however we should still have to listen
because we must think what is inevitable
for preliminary
let me give a hint on how to listen let
me give a little hint on how to listen
the point is not to listen to a series
of propositions but rather to follow the
movement of showing when I read that
part again let me give a hint a little
hint on how to listen the point is not
to listen to a series of propositions
but rather to follow the movement of
showing thank you nice okay cool
I'm recording that too perfect perfect
yeah and I think one thing that I've
noticed and this helps for also you know
you saw you wake up in the morning and
you're not you feel maybe would you feel
kind of some lassitude and you feel
maybe a bit lethargic or unmotivated but
you know that you have to you know that
you have a sequence of tasks that you
need to accomplish but you don't feel
disposed to any of them and you need a
mechanism for motivating yourself to
actually tend to the things that need
tending and the thing that I find
increasingly useful is the realization
that putting myself into a certain state
of activity will naturally precondition
the motivation required for actually
undertaking that activity itself right
so most people feel I think think okay I
have to go and do X
and in order to go and do X I really
have to feel like going and doing X
right so I muster my motivation I Center
my will and then I proceed and when in
fact I find its VIP that's very much the
inverse is that in order to be aroused
into a mode of engagement matched to a
particular activity you have to first
immerse yourself in the activity in
order to condition the engagement like I
find that's very true of writing right
if I don't feel like writing the most
useful thing I can do is sit down and
start writing because inevitably the
state of engagement the way in which the
relationship is then lit when I sit down
to 10 to the activity well naturally
condition the and retrofit me with the
motivation to actually continue it as
opposed to sitting on my own you know
thinking okay I go to do this now I
should get up and do this but not
feeling really not feeling the will so
the idea that putting yourself into
certain states in order to condition
yourself to understand activities that
to me is an example of understanding how
mutable character is and that sort of a
that's a way of using the wisdom of
aspiration the wisdom of aspired future
States as a way of setting the table for
yourself to then be willing to take on
certain tasks right it's like well I am
NOT the kind of person right now who can
do this but if I if I courted myself
with X number of conditions I know that
I will become the kind of person who can
then do X Y s so being able to then play
with your identification and that like
that to me is sort of it's a it's a
motivational kind of wisdom because it
just you you realize that you where we
are so utterly beholden to the forces
that in which we're ensconced at any
particular moment in time right got it
makes so much sense when you think about
that I add this picture of well how do
you get a bunch of a bunch of in
stink lifts or poor and instinct animals
to do the right thing like culture on
some level is this yeah you know we we
talk about like in the West how free we
are but actually I think it's more fair
to say we are deeply civilized and we
behave very very well precisely because
of the thousands of years and hundreds
of years of of history that's embedded
in all of our social practices right
such that we get up and we are inside
and right boundaries and lines and
structures that call out to us the lines
that we don't have to think enough we're
walking inside of right and so like
there's so many ways in which I wake up
in the morning and I'm in a room and
there's I'm already thinking in terms of
what's already laid out for me is this
is private and then there's a sense of
public out there and I can prepare
myself to be public all those things are
embedded in the architecture of our of
our room and it's thinking about like
imagine imagine if every morning you
woke up and you had to like do all that
you had to like you had to basically
create culture from scratch start from
nothing yeah yeah well yeah so there's
there's a way in which so many I would
imagine like our motivate but
motivational wisdom and the way it
breaks down ray is is given by the
literal ontological cultural structures
that fashioned us and then you're
talking about like a clay right so all
that's kind of built up on right and
then we wake up inside of it and then
there's this one place or the individual
right has a little bit of choice there
and it doesn't feel like doing the next
thing right in some way that generative
sense of like alright right now I can't
I don't feel like writing which is
interesting to think about like so they
for The Horizon upon which I write is
precisely the thing that I don't feel
but I can imagine or remember feeling
and then that becomes the thing that
consolidates right my will right in that
sense but what's also interesting about
with like yeah we'll at that moment I
don't have the will to just sit down and
write but I have the will to to
understand that if I give myself over to
this activity if I surrender my will
right over to this activity that the
will will then be taken up by these
other processes there's a certain kind
of faith I notice and an argument that I
have right with those kinds of thoughts
right you know right you know I think
that you're probably is right that's
right
I would imagine and really appreciating
to because you're having you're at a
time in your life where you have like
more open free time where you know I
think that people people who work
corporate job like a regular schedule
probably fantasize about like working
from home or something like that but
then the moment you work from home you
realize how indebted you are mm-hmm to
all of this structure right that Hetal
and hmm so what's the weight map is all
open you and there's it can be
tremendously challenging to enculturate
yourself right absolutely
mm-hmm it is it is and that's why you
have to find a way to Reese amia late
those structures and to redevelop them
and personalize them as though they were
personal relationships sort of like I
know that in the moment right now I
might feel prone to my solitude but then
the moment I come and start talking to
guy I'm immediately going to be shifted
into a different modus of engagement I'm
immediately going to be called out and
reframed around my discursive
relationship with you and Who I am and
how I feel is going to change quite
comprehensively and so I know that even
if I do
feel like accompaniment moment I put
myself into dialogue with you the
appetite for accompaniment is going to
come as part for the course in the
territory and it's very very similar
with even a solitary task I know as soon
as I put myself into rapport when I I
will by wrecking my rapport with the
activity I will recollect the kind of
motivation and concentration required to
actually undertake the task so it's you
were saying you know you were talking
about it as a memory aright as a
remembrance of your of a particular I
particularly disposed attitude and then
really the wisdom of the structure and
the wisdom of using the structure is
remembering how to remember right if I
can remember how to remember that
relationship then I'm going to be able
to retrieve the memory even if it's not
readily available to me right so it's so
I think these structures are really sort
of these are these are of these sort of
proxies for for access and availability
I might not have this state it might not
be imminent to me at this moment but if
I have the means to retrieve the memory
of the state and use it to actually
rehabilitate and habituate the state
then it's always within my access even
if it's not present to me at this given
moment and I think the wisdom of these
structures especially insofar as they
can be personally appropriated is to be
able to access the states required to
undertake the tasks required in your
higher order desire right what you want
to be wanting as it were at any given
time right right I'm just I think I'm
just well what it's just good to see you
and talk with you again I missed you
when you're on your trip you - yeah - I
could have the same yeah just
I appreciate the just getting right out
I'm just jumping right into it you know
and we're in that that I feel surrounded
by and in by in this way
you know so much affinity I'm glad to be
doing this with you yeah yeah me too me
too
oh yeah I missed ya
yeah and and it's interesting because
you know I think about for this for this
video is just um
just to set some context for a I guess
you can call it a project or I was
thinking like a rig like just a regular
time where we meet once a week and we we
walk through the dialogues together
right and I guess depending about like
how many inner lockers there are in each
dialogue we can invite you know John or
or Jordan or all the different people
that we've been talking to to kind of
come along with us
right in different dialogues I think it
would be fun but having you and I be
kind of the you know the ones the ones
that are kind of like will be kind of
like the ground for it right and then
and then it's especially like getting
hold of the of the Platina the Platonic
dialogues that in reading them in the
order that they originally read them in
the Platonic on that I think that what's
exciting to me about that is I would
imagine because the order there was an
order and it's not it's not
chronological there's that there's a
there's a wisdom in the order that I
want to apprehend right or disclosed in
it so so one of the things I was
imagining is like what's excited about
doing it once a week is I want to not
only learn what we're reading right and
be affected by what we're reading but
note but every read be able to talk
about the way in which were impregnated
by the reading like how our lives our
lives look different right and all the
different transformations and shifts and
tensions that that I'm sure that on some
on some level in these kinds of things I
find they end up being a context in
which my life gathers around right
I think it's a I think it's a fantastic
idea and I think it obviously it harkens
to a a pedagogical style that's kind of
drifted now into obsolescence and
reviving the entire style of pedagogy is
obviously like it's a central feature of
our collective project obviously it's
John's a mine and and and and ours and
um so I think yeah it's it's a kind of
philosophic experiment that is the likes
of which are now very rarely attempted I
think I told you in the previous
conversation that even though I took
many courses when I was when I was still
at school that that revolved around any
number of the dialogues the exercise of
actually reading them aloud in any kind
of dramatic fashion is something that I
only recall once and at the time felt I
mean it was interesting but it also felt
so it felt I think it made people very
self-conscious precisely of of how it
was something that just wasn't it wasn't
it wasn't it was it hadn't been
habituated into the into the into the
Platonic education and so it seemed
almost maybe uncouth to people that they
had to be doing this but but the idea
that it's sort of fallen so it's fallen
out of the orbit of such things it's
like right you wouldn't you just you
just wonder how conceivably that could
have happened right but anyway this is
all to say it's a period that India and
and ritualizing it with a certain
regularity and and then seeing also I
mean in addition to the in addition to
the the fact that obviously the process
will evolve as the dialogue to progress
but but it's not only the dialogues that
will change but our format of
interacting with the dialogues will
change yeah and that will be interesting
as well because it's something that I
think we'll have to improvise our way
through to a certain degree as we
acquire more and more comfort
the project itself and understand how to
orient it in such a way that we
optimized the experience right so even
the way we meet at how we read it how 10
gent shal the the readings are how much
we want to background or foreground the
reading with historicity or or footnote
it with sort of more you know incidental
you know tidbits of information that
kind of thing I mean there's all of the
sort of surrounding the surrounding
procedure of it if something that is
bound to change and bad - of all this we
go along so I'm actually just as
interested in that I'm interested to see
how we begin and then how it changes
yeah yeah that you know I'm a few a few
different things with this is so one of
the things I could probably put more
concrete language that has revealed
itself in these dialogues right that
we've been acting with and since I
started you know doing these these kind
I mean I've been do having these I mean
I would say my life is made of these
dialogues in Who I am is made of these
kinds of you know relationships and as
you said in one of your rivet I'm what I
am is constituted is cut is its
Constitution is made up of all those
relationships throughout my life and
I've I love the way that you put that
and through but since doing this in
putting them out public for everybody to
watch and having a sense of a living
relationship with so many different
people and an ongoing conversation that
in pregs impregnates write each other
conversation with each other right that
I'm noticing things that are emerging
that were talked about in the beginning
but like have a different character now
when that when I've heard them a lot of
them them and one of them is
kind of like talking about you know
John's how John would describe it is
like an ecology of practices right well
let's see I think you're frozen can you
hear me
I can okay good I can hear you yes we'll
just work with the internet connection
okay I will have oh yeah I'll have all
have resolved this this discontinuation
time we get into our platonic readings
okay good good good boy would that be a
mess maybe ignore Socrates you know left
hand and in the work right now in some
way we don't understand
[Laughter]
maybe yes the charitable reading I'll
take it yeah it really culminated in
this last conversation I had with with
John Verve a key and Johannes which we
were talking about in johannes is a
heidi garyun scholar and philosopher and
we talked to a lot about like western
metaphysics and like the history and the
in the forgetfulness of being that
Heidegger talks a lot about and which is
a deep topic that that I think you just
continually understand more and more and
more has that character to it
of an of a you can't ever really get
super clear about it but you can just
always be in becoming of it yielding
more the more that you look at it and
not one of the big questions I had going
into that conversation was like okay so
how how does one stand in relationship
right with in heidecker's terminology
the withdrawal of the sense of being
right and how do you appropriately stand
in it right while deeply understanding
your of
time the unfolding of that temper ality
they were not you're not creating create
history right you're you history's
realized right through us and we're
inside of it so how do you how do you
respond to something so intense is
meaninglessness right in a way that's
it's in spite relationship with what the
actual phenomena that that's happening
and so one I know one of the ways that I
think that we're all kind of one way of
responding is this conversation right
these conversations and there's this
kind of element for me in them of kind
of wading through the darkness like kind
of not really like constantly being in a
certain sense listening to the whisper
right enormous E of what's happening
right but seeing if you can heat begin
to harken into the the the thing that's
concealed but yet is is is whispering
and it's withdrawal right and then
John's response to that being like the
the meaning crisis in framing it in the
meaning crisis and the sense of the
ecology of practices and one of the
things that we really became clear to me
in that last conversation was what when
John said you know what's missing for me
and a lot of these like I find a lot of
what he said is like what's missing for
me a lot of much practices that he's
been participating in like meditation
and you know different kind of
embodiment practicing in circles and
he's like is philosophy a-- right that
in and i would i would say that in my
experience i've a wink philosophy ax in
circling right but to really through the
back door right because people's people
have a lot of inertia that comes up when
even the know
philosophy happens right they don't
really see it as something that's
substantial in the way one woman's life
right they kind of see it more acting it
makes sense because I think in many ways
philosophy has become you know the pure
academia and so a lot of the people who
are seeking more connectedness and do
doing these kinds of practices almost
see that the practices are a way to
defend themselves or ground themselves
in something other than philosophy right
so this is kind of notice notion about
like if you if it appears into anything
philosophical people go oh you're just
in your head like right get out of your
head getting your you know there's a lot
of ropes a lot of the tropes of the
human potential movement become kind of
like you know a club that people beat
over each other you know I'm ahead with
in criticism as as in the realm of
philosophy were the enemy and so there
was this kind of dialectic that we were
having it would well know like John was
saying like no it's not I'm not
advocating for philosophy per se like
I'm neutral about whether or not that's
necessary but what he's saying is this
actually may be necessary right for the
convergence of the ontological the
cognitive psychological and the
existential that that we need practices
that have a connect us with the thing
that connects all those things together
right that transcends and includes and
integrates in and involves the machinery
that that distributes that wisdom all
the way up right and how do we do it in
a way that isn't isn't going backwards
in making claims that aren't viable to
us right anymore which is kind of like
as you would say I think would be me
you know the dying star of Christianity
right not really or becoming Christian
or be
coming that again right but looking at
the mistakes of it but also looking at
the machinery practices right and evoke
being practice this and so I really had
walked away with with that sense of like
yeah I think what one of the things that
motivates me to do this project with you
right and to do it the way that we are
at least started is to reawaken the
sense of philosophy a-- as being a
necessary transformative agent right to
connect us with our own ground or heart
or mind right and to we that which is
beyond all of that right in a in a felt
way restore the sense of philosophy yeah
right as an as is crucial and necessary
as the other things that that have a lot
more claim on us right but that's
actually to not have that maybe actually
detrimental in some way or unincluded
and i see that a lot in like it
especially because i live in the Bay
Area which is like that you know it's
the well it's kind of like we're the
world's pouring out from right on in all
of its glory and all of its all of its
weirdness but it's also art it's that
it's the heart of the human potential
movement or where it started right and
so there's all kinds of dual there's all
kinds of assumed dualities to separate
these two things right that people take
on because it's part of the culture you
don't even notice that they're taking it
on until the opposite they're your
opposite and then they're hostile
towards it right so I actually would and
I want to get a sense of for me as one
of the as one of wonders of something
like the human potential movement over
the iteration of it is to move is to is
to actually kind of bring back that
sense philosophy because for me that
that's circle it came
circling is has not been a therapeutic
endeavor it hasn't been a psychological
personal growth endeavor it's it's a
different domain it's been I would say
that circling has been precisely the
thing that's inspired me about it and
what what's possible and this is where I
think it's an in dialogue dialogue in
general is awakened a sense of a
mystical thread that runs through
conversations and can be transformative
and that like there's the personal
domain right like the sense of what it's
like being with you and like the
personal intimacy right but what happens
when we bring in the philosophy ax where
the personal can can be can can be
intimate with what calls us for the
conversation and be in and in a certain
sense starts to grant the dialog right
with each other in this I vow connection
mm-hm
and so I was that's where I really
thought reading you at you're in John's
article that you wrote that some it
hasn't been peered I think it's in peer
review right yeah right now it's in it's
in peer review and so we have and we I'm
sort of still sort of in draft form at
the moment I guess right so we're gonna
take that I think that even makes it
even better right we're gonna take we're
gonna take the draft of that paper and I
thought it like a really good idea by
the way that paper just rocks I love
that paper man thank you guys did such a
good job
thank you yeah I thought it was it it
was a labor of love he did that's that's
absolutely it's it was a good example of
something that began as one thing and
then landed somewhere utterly utterly
different there was a it commutated it's
orientation it's fundamental purpose its
scope its its volumes
I think ended up exceeding anything that
either of us intended simply because we
became so absorbed into it and it's a
very it took on a life of its own that
seemed to have its own agency and it
vectored itself in its own direction so
in some ways it was we were very much
along for the ride which like what a
humbling feeling that is and it's also a
feeling of like you know you and your
work reaches a certain velocity you feel
as though you're trying to actually keep
up with it as opposed to it keeping up
with you that that the the entity that
emerges is a consequence of that work
that is neither you nor the exercise but
something over and above either of you
or in the case of John and I something
certainly over and between us is imbues
the whole process with a certain
humility and a sense of intrinsic
significance that can't quite be
accounted for by the dimensions of any
given project
so such was the case for this chapter
right that's did yeah yeah I suppose we
thank you that's very kind of you and it
was obviously and so when it does when
it does come to full fruition and anyone
who certainly takes it up and who has
also seen our dialogo
with you and I and John and Jordan will
will not cannot but see the resemblance
obviously the that there's certainly an
evolution of thinking that is that is
that is being transmitted from one
medium into the other which is also
really neat to me and this is a this is
a filler this is sort of a this the
prototype roto typical philosophic
drafting process yeah yeah just so it
yeah I I kept having that sense of I
kept having the sense when I read it
that as I was reading it you started to
what you what I was reading I
imagine was so much very processed that
was that wrote it like it's very fractal
in that way and Yunus in a certain way I
could yes but by by by hopeful design
yeah yeah like I just really you really
got that sense that like you're like
whoa you're in the presence of the thing
and then you're having to draw on
language and vocabulary to try to bring
this in and so just I get this sense of
like new words have different meaning
and like that I love that experience of
where and I love that cut that
experience of like when you were when
when what you're talking about it you
realize is the thing that's talking
right those moments where it just comes
comes through in the bright the police
in which the police is and the technical
soundness in which called into
articulation was was it was a sense of
like oh my god if we I gotta break look
this in this way otherwise it's gonna
slip away but it's the thing that's
happening right now is the sense I got I
could imagine I kept imagining you and
John I'm so talking I'm so gratified
that you had that experience I'm so
gratified that you had that experience
because it's it's it's a Wonders thing
to to know that the experience of
interacting with it as a reader in some
form is I'm gonna find is is is somehow
similar to the process of actually of
actually creating it create creating it
sounds far too willful for the process
I've just described it's more like the
midwifery again right right simply
helping to deliver it because it
certainly doesn't feel like it doesn't
feel like a like a premeditated form of
design at all precisely because it's
it's a it's a developmental emergence of
a kind anyway it's so it's it's yeah
it's incredibly gratifying to hear that
thank you yeah
and I just thought given that what
you're one of the big things that that
that my understanding of the purpose of
that is to is to awaken and and reveal
this the Platonic dialogues and the
Socratic inquiry and dialect like all
the things there's a lot of that into
how is that relevant now and even
necessary now right and so it's really
kind of had this way of paper hey what
is it oftentimes like I find the
Platonic dialogues oftentimes have this
kind of or portrayed in this very
classical dry logical sense right like
you read the classics it's like
considered the classic it kind of has
this a magnet right sense of no
relevance to your current situation just
historical like this history of
philosophy but there's a way in where
you're saying like no like this stuff is
this stuff is a temporal in a sense
right it transcends a lot of that and
this is how in fact we're necessary now
yes then perhaps it's ever been
yes and so it really situates that
wisdom in our modern situation and the
ways that you the way that you open up
in terms of the loss of the second
person is you articulate the problem I
thought was really brilliant and it's a
great lead thank you
I think it's a great lead-in to spec
context for how what we're gonna be
doing however long it takes right to go
through the dialogues it's a great it's
a great context for that right right
right
well thank you really very very much and
and it's interesting too because I think
yeah what you said about the a temper
morality is exactly right because so
much of what we're trying to do in the
throes of do logos is to actually
surface ourselves from the temporal
entrapments and the noise of the
temporal and
fragments that form sort of the way that
in which we we revolve on sort of a
quotidian basis right that's the the
apprehension of eternity in some form is
and I use the term form right advisedly
is the is the aim of the dialogic
process right be the in viewing the
temporal with the eternal and and so
because and and then also the idea like
there are some really fundamental
axiomatic I think misunderstandings that
have just I think inscribed themselves
prima facie in our understanding of
philosophy and meat and the role of
philosophy over the course of time and
perhaps the most the most pervasive of
those is the notion that philosophy is
somehow separable as a category of
experience or as a or as one among a
taxonomy of activities that we can
partake over not the same so same
mistake that's been made of religion
right the idea that it's a native
category among experiences as opposed to
some as opposed to a way of formulating
our experience of being really large and
I think that one thing that we're trying
to do at least with philosophy ax in the
meaning that John implies when he uses
the term yeah is to understand if we are
if we are as Heidegger suggested living
within a question of being then
philosophy ax is the exercise of
formulating that question iteratively
again and again and again with
appreciating exactitude yeah right that
philosophy is the practice of of
philosophy is the practice of like I
would you know we the
question of being as is a is a perfusion
right it's something that's very very
difficult to retrieve and refine in ways
that give it some kind of some kind of
formal and actionable presence and
philosophy is I think as a as an ecology
of practices let's say is the process of
interacting with our fundamental
question of being and and and and to
afford ourselves a graduating conformity
with the most incisive version of that
question right that would there's we
don't Dees from philosophy like there's
no there's no there's no separation that
philosophy is simply the reckoning of
the question of being and and and it we
possessed of it so you know I think so I
think that perhaps one one one one
feature or one goal of this project is
to collapse together again the
identification between the question of
being that we live out and the
enterprise of philosophy a-- insofar as
it's a psycho technology in the proper
sense of the term before refining and
distilling the question of being in a
pragmatic way yeah that we can better
interface with reality right with what
is what is in most and and and and most
fundamentally real right the
approximation of reality by the endless
iteration of the question of being and
that's the philosophic Enterprise at
least as I understand it you know like
there's a like a million etiologies for
how what philosophy means and how it
came to be and fundamentally what its
dimensions are
but firm idiot is simply that it's
simply an exercise of the an exercising
conformity of the self to the question
of being yes and that is the philosophic
enterprise and I think then it certainly
is it insofar as the Socratic project is
concerned yes and then the deal the
dialogic form the dialogic conformity
right between us is precisely the craft
techne yeah of that that most ultimate
of question posing right in that tech
like I love that like this sense of the
a certain sense respirating restoring
tech naming out of its dominant position
right in the age of technology but in in
a position of that which in its craft
reveals what it itself can't craft it's
always subordinate something and I
really like how you set how you wove
that together of like it's it's not just
romanticism right um just espousing the
glory of the of the natural or something
like right at that sentence there's a
rigor right to our propositions right to
to the way we make sense of it and
actually technically more and more
profound but when you talked about the
pragmatism I really appreciated that
because I felt this sense of like yeah
this is where we started or the
propositional and what what gives it its
measure as a valid proposition isn't its
ability to make truth claims necessarily
but the ability to stand on them and
reveal more of the mystery right of
right that our propositions laid down
you know really see this in your writing
right in the in the paper gonna write
like on one level it is profoundly
technically precise but it's like
reading poetry
at the same time that sweet spot of like
that that place of where we're yes were
as we're going along were were we're
making sense and as we make sense we we
put down a a stone but beneath our feet
right before we step on it right and so
that we can step more and towards this
center as we circumambulate around it
and where I really want to make sense of
like one of the things that we're gonna
drink one of the things that I think
that that people like about a lot of
these dialogues and then I'm hearing
about right today they have a hard time
describing what what it is that they
like about it but there's an attraction
is that it's very rare to equate the
quake the unlike the
the prat those practices that that have
one become more knowledgeable without it
with that like without the aim of it
being directly utilitarian
useful right and and I think that one of
the things that kind of philosophy a--
is a space where what's being talked
about and this is where Socrates I think
continually is misunderstood right but
with a kind of trickery continually
reveals in the dialogue which is no
there's a way there's a way of knowing
and knowledge that it that cannot be
used by you right but maybe we can
develop a kind of listening that is
powerful but not immediately be
consumable or useful and so like a lot
of the dialogues from hotel is like it
they're frustrating you're meandering
like like yes you're solving puzzles and
you realize you're like the act of
solving the puzzle like dissembles the
puzzle that you're solving it and it's
it it's not like it's not like it's not
entertaining in this immediate way it's
not really you you precisely are lost to
the relevance of how this connects to
the original thing we were talking about
and everything and you go through this
whole process and at the end like people
are like ah I feel I don't feel like we
at all have the answer to that question
but somehow I don't care I just want to
spend more time with Socrates or my
visions more clear that's my answer
exactly because because by the end of
the dialogue exactly yeah exactly
because by the end of the dialogue I am
become more I am becoming more in the
likeness of the question itself right
yes I become I I begin to to to it's
like I my
my my my being is suffused with the
question such that I I I asked it with
with deeper import and and the scope of
the scope of conceivable possibility
that that question is able to access is
deepened and broadened as a consequence
of becoming more in it's like this right
I can ask the same question but as if
but if I am myself in more in likeness
to the question then the question has a
breath now that it didn't have before
and it has a it has a a the the question
itself has changed modes yes well yes
yeah it's in that the gist the I would
say that we are as as time has gone on
in my lifetime anyways the amount the
amount that that that a space like that
you're talking about that way that kind
of need a sense of of wisdom and knowing
and engaging with these things that
aren't immediately useful right but yet
somehow grants the eyes that have us see
things and to be able to be useful right
like that didn't collar exactly
tolerance for hanging out in that
process has become less and less and
less in just my lifetime I've noticed oh
yeah so so this is a justice it's just
for the listener and for ourselves is
that what we're doing here is not
something that's immediately gonna be
able to like we're not gonna solve any
problem right and if we did we didn't
mean to
but there's but were were espousing like
I want a like a like a spout opportunity
for people to dwell and when it right
which can give the eyes of clarity but
you could never be clear about in some
final way and and to start to value that
love that that's right and and because
if you is whitelisted a david white
would say where he loves I love this
distinction he makes he's like he's like
this link between identity and levels of
attention right and you say that that
the more one deepens their ability pay
attention the more one's identity
changes in relationship to that
attention right because if you start to
see absolutely right so what we're
talking about is like in a certain sense
is developing and exercising the
machinery right that that that grant
something like the ability to make like
more deeper more refined more inclusive
attention that allowed the world who
come forward in such a way that you'll
that requires someone that someone who
could respond to such a world and in
that sense like it becomes very very
very pertinent right but in it that not
to be as it is you give to open up to
like when it hurts and when you're
confused and when it's the struggle why
be in that struggle it's precisely
because of that right frankly yes right
right right
exactly that's a well said guy and then
if and then to send then recollect this
back into the Socratic Enterprise I
might say that if the the purpose of
this sort of the purpose of this the
Linkous as a form of inquiry
it is such that if the if the aperture
of our attention is adjusted by the
questions we live through then the
Socratic project and certainly the
version of the Socratic project that we
are taking up is an exercise of
enlarging that aperture right the the
the the the the torso of ours that faces
the cosmos and how exposed we choose to
make yeah so rich I tell you what I need
to get some water and to adjust a few
things over here look let's put the
video on pause okay and then we let me
come back okay I'll try to start
repeating okay all right well just put
sounds good
okay so Chris and I where we can't you
just get took took took a break and and
of course we ended up talking and then
it it ran in we used up all of our time
allotted for awesome conversation that
we just got in um so my sense is my
sense is the best thing to do would be
to really just kind of wrap this
conversation up with any any setting up
any context around what we're doing
right about what we're gonna start when
we start reading and then they just have
this be the first video just as setting
context so good to you
yeah that sounds good to me I think that
I think that they're the themes and
intentions are pretty pretty clear
they're pretty clear and they're
obviously shared between us so I don't
know that there's too much stuff to say
other than this is a this is a wonderful
experimental and playful process I think
that that we're very knowingly and sort
of conscient Lee entering into and I'm
quite excited about it for its fruits
for its its intrinsic enjoyment and for
for whatever come of it so yeah I'm
looking forward to beginning yes and and
also just for the for if this inspires
are there is one of the big like a lot
of I've gotten a lot of common and
people emailing me and such you know
really wanting to participate and
immediately what I found out is like the
the nature of the cock like the
explosive nature of infinity that starts
to erupt from that right is is can be
quite little and unlimited so one of the
things I would be really thought would
be cool to do is that I can make a
playlist on my channel right where we
were we had these videos and if other
people want to participate and they want
to make their own videos in
relationships or reading and want to do
you know conversations in place and that
are inspired in a relationship to words
that they're doing why don't why do you
guys just do that and then and then send
me a link to those and I like put them
you know put you know make notice of it
and well you can just send me the link
and then I can title it so it it links
and I could just post those underneath
our videos so that way everybody who's
participated and you can listen in on
what the other thinking is around doing
and the impacts so I thought that would
be cool to gather those in the same
place in some way in a way of a way of
inviting participation right such that
in a way that we can
actually what right I don't know if I'd
be if I'll have to always have time to
listen to everything that's right but I
want to give everybody the option to do
to participate that way yeah I I think
we're inevitably gonna come up on sort
of the the economy of the process will
have very natural constraints and time
being the chiefest among them
so I guess well I think we'll probably
have to adjust in an ongoing way how we
how we approach the question of more
communal participation I mean I as like
the spirit of it I think is is exactly
in accordance with the practice itself
and the undertaking and I liked what we
did I liked the process of their radios
obviously it's
it's not like practicable to be doing it
as frequently as we would like simply
because of how how time-consuming it is
and how many worthwhile comments there
are very very thoughtful comments to go
through so I think maybe what we can do
as well as we proceed is to have our
eyes peeled for different ways of of
enveloping the enveloping folks who are
who are along for the ride
sort of in the margins of the
conversation and bringing them into the
crosshairs of its scope and we'll just
sort of see we'll be open to creative
suggestions too on that front I think
yeah totally all right all right I look
forward to this thank you Chris me too
thank you guy
all right you have a good day